James H. Etheridge and family collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
James H. Etheridge and family collection
1827-1937
Ms Coll 62
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
10
James H. Etheridge was a gynecologist who became Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology at Rush Medical College. The collection contains biographical materials, correspondence of Etheridge, correspondence of Etheridge's wife's family (including the correspondence of Heman G. Powers, a Chicago businessman), Etheridge's writings, his patient records, ephemera from medical societies, photographs, and certificates and diplomas.
Biographical / Historical
James Henry Etheridge, gynecologist, was born in St. Johnsville, New York, March 20, 1844. His physician father, Francis B. Etheridge, taught J. H. Etheridge medicine before the latter entered Rush Medical College, Chicago, in 1866. After graduation in 1869, Etheridge began a general practice in Evanston, Illinois. In 1870, he married Harriet Elizabeth Powers, of Evanston, daughter of wealthy businessman Heman G. Powers and Sarah Throop Powers. They traveled abroad and and he visited hospitals in London. On his return in 1871, he set up practice in Chicago and became part of the teaching faculty of Rush Medical College. At first, he was a successful general practitioner, and then he specialized in gynecology. In 1889, he became Professor of Gynecology at Rush Medical College, and in 1892, Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology. He was active in medical organizations and served as President of the Chicago Medical Society and the Chicago Gynecological Society. At the height of his career, he died suddenly on February 9, 1899. He was known as a man of good nature and wit, and as a skillful and rapid operator.
Heman George Powers, wealthy Chicago businessman and father-in-law to James H. Etheridge, was born in Keeseville, New York in 1820. He married Sarah Throop in 1843 in Vergenne, Vermont. About 1857, he moved to Chicago and built up a large wholesale grocery business under the name Durand Bros. and Powers. The business was destroyed in the Chicago fire of 1871. Powers then entered the banking business and became president of a bank in Chicago. In retirement, he lived in Evanston, Illinois, and spent time at a farm he owned in Wisconsin.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence of J. H. Etheridge from 1894 until his death in 1899, correspondence of the Powers and Throop families back to the 1850s, medical case records and payment ledgers, talks and published articles, Rush Medical College ephemera, medical society ephemera, diplomas and certificates including some awarded to Etheridge's father, photographs, and the many obituaries written on Etheridge.
Arrangement
Organized into 8 series: 1. Biographical information /Obituaries. 2. Correspondence of James H. Etheridge. 3. Powers/Throop family correspondence. 4. J. H. Etheridge writings. 5. Organizations and societies. 6. Medical practice. 7. Oversize box: Additional patient records, correspondence, and miscellany. 8. Flat box: Large photographs, certificates, and diplomas.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by a descendant, James Grant Young, from the estate of Margaret Grant Young, 2017.
Related Materials
Additional materials related to James H. Etheridge were donated by James Grant Young, from the estate of Margaret Grant Young, to the Rush University Medical Center Archives.
Surgery; Obstetrics; Medicine, Military; Societies, Medical; Medical education; Gynecology; Cervix uteri--Cancer--Surgery; Iron industry and trade--United States; Account books; Certificates; Correspondence; Diaries; Gynecologists -- Illinois -- Chicago; Businessmen -- Illinois -- Chicago; Medical records; Ingals, E. Fletcher (Ephraim Fletcher), 1848-1918; Park, Roswell, 1852-1914; Etheridge, James Henry, 1844-1899; Powers, Heman George, 1820-1892; Powers, Sarah E. Throop, 1825-1902; Harper, William Rainey, 1856-1906; Henrotin, Fernand, 1847-1906; Hyde, James Nevins, 1840-1910; Illinois. National Guard; Pryor, William R., 1857-1904; J. & J. Rogers Iron Company; Powers family; Throop family; Lea Brothers & Company; Moline Malleable Iron Co.; Rush Medical College; Etheridge, Harriet Elizabeth Powers
- Biographical information /Obituaries, Series 1
  - Correspondence of Etheridge Grant on the disposal of J.H. Etheridge's Personal effects, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    Etheridge Grant was a descendent of J.H. and Harriet (Hattie) Etheridge. Their daughter Fanny married John MacGregor Grant.
  - Handwritten obituary on Rush Medical College stationary (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Resolutions of the Senior Class of Rush Medical college on the death of Prof. Etheridge, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Folder contains the handwritten Resolutions as sent to Etheridge's family and an issue The Corpuscle (April 1899), the alumni journal of Rush Medical College, with the printed resolution.
  - Obituary: Issue of The American Gynaecological and Obstetrical Journal, 1899 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Obituary: Issue of the Chicago Medical Recorder, 1899 February (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Obituary: issue of The Corpuscle, 1899 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
    The Corpuscle was the "Official Organ of the Alumni Association of Rush Medical College, Chicago, Ill." The article, "James Henry Etheridge, A.M., M.D.: In Memoriam" (volume 8, pp. 273-276 and portrait) was presented to the faculty by Prof. James B. Herrick.
  - Obituary: Issue of Journal of the American Medical Association, 1899 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Obituary: Issue of Journal of Scientific Medicine, 1899 February (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Obituary: Issue of The Medical Dial, 1899 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Obituary: Issue of the Revue de gynecologie et de chirurgie abdominale, 1899 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Obituary: Issue of the Tri-State Medical Journal and Practitioner, 1899 February (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Obituary: Issue of The Chicago Daily Tribune, 1899 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Obituary: Issue of the Chicago Evening Post, 1899 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Obituary: Issue of The Chicago Times-Herald, 1899 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Other obituaries, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Newspaper clippings and printed report, "Monthly Meetings of the Alumnae Association of the Illinois Training School for Nurses," February 2, 1899 [sic], containing an obituary of Etheridge on page 8. For ten years Etheridge had been lecturer and physician to the School.
  - Caricature of Etheridge and poem on minced pie, by C.J.P.U. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Other publications that mention Etheridge, 1896-1929 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Presbyterian Hospital of the City of Chicago, Bulletin, 1929 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Contains a history of the hospital that mentions J. H. Etheridge.
  - James H. Etheridge - photographs (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence of James H. Etheridge, 1894-1899; Series 2
  The collection contains only correspondence from 1894 to 1899. The alphabetical files contain mainly letters received, although there is an occasional draft of a letter by Etheridge. Among his correspondents were women patients. Etheridge asked patients to write to him on the anniversary of their operations.
  The incoming correspondence was housed in two boxes of Amberg's Popular Letter File sold by Amberg File & Index Co., Chicago. Many of the letters were not accurately filed under the proper letter in the index.
  Someone, likely Mrs. Etheridge, who lived into the 1920s, annotated a number of the letters.
  In Box 4 there are carbons of typed correspondence by date sent by Dr. Etheridge from September 1897 to his death in February 1899.
  - Correspondence, A (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: "Barkee" and "Bar and Kee" (a relative) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, B (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, C (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, D (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Etheridge, Annie and Locke (sister-in-law? and brother) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Etheridge, Francis (Frank), brother (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, E (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, F (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, G (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Harper, William R., President of University of Chicago (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Henrotin, Fernand (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Hyde, James Nevins (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, H (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Ingals, E. Fletcher (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, J (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, K (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Lea Brothers & Co., Phliadelphia (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, M (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, N (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, O (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Park, Roswell (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Powers, Heman R., brother-in-law, 1895-1897 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    General
    There is an obituary of Heman R. Powers in Box 6, Folder 43.
  - Correspondence: Powers, Heman R., brother-in-law, 1898-1899 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Pryor, W. R., nephew (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, P (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, R (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Senn, N. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    The correspondent is not Etheridge's colleague Nicholas Senn, but rather a younger man going into federal service.
  - Correspondence: Stone, E. M. and Mary R. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    R. M. Stone, M.D. was a physician in Omaha, Nebraska and his wife, Mary, was a patient of Etheridge. The case was discussed in detail.
  - Correspondence, S (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, T. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, V (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, W (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: "Alice," a patient (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence concerning calcium carbide in operations for cancer of the cervix, 1898-1899 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    In the issue of Journal of the American Medical Association for July 2, 1898, Etheridge had published "A Note on the Treatment of Carcinoma of the Uterus," in which he asked for information from others on treatment by calcium carbide. These responces from physicians were placed in a file by Etheridge.
  - Correspondence: "Military", 1894-1896 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    These materials were grouped by Etheridge. He had served in the Civil War and had later served in the First Brigade, Illinois National Guard.
  - Correspondence: "Military", 1897-1898 and no date (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Carbons of letters by James H. Etheridge, 1897 September 20-1898 December 5 (Box 4, Item 1)
    Bound volume of carbon copies of typed letters by Etheridge arranged chronologically, September 20, 1897-December 5, 1898. Volume contains 1004 numbered pages plus an index at the beginning of the volume. See next folder.
  - Carbons of letters by James H. Etheridge, 1898 December 5-1899 February 9 (Box 4, Item 2)
    Folder containing unbound carbon copies of letters from December 5, 1898 to February 9, 1899, the day of his death. Carbons are paged from 1 to 103.
- Powers/Throop family correspondence, Series 3
  This is correspondence from Harriet (Hattie) Powers Etheridge's side of the family, collected by Hattie Etheridge and her heirs. The letters were stored in several boxes of Amberg's Patent Indexes. Hattie Etheridge was the daughter of Heman G. Powers and Sarah (Throop) Powers. The bulk of this collection consists of letters to Hattie Etheridge's mother and father, Sarah Throop Powers and Heman G. Powers. Heman G. Powers's correspondence includes information on his various business dealings. The series also contains some letters by and to Hattie Etheridge, her children, and other relatives and friends.
  - Correspondence of Harriet (Hattie) Powers Etheridge and children, Subseries 1
    Harriet (Hattie) Elizabeth Powers was the daughter of Heman G. Powers and Sarah (Throop) Powers. She was born in 1848 and married James H. Etheridge on June 22, 1870. Her daughters were Fanny Etheridge (Grant) and Emily (or Emma) Etheridge (Brewer)(1877-1924). As of 1920, she was living in Chicago with Emily and Emily's husband William Brewer.
    - Hattie Elizabeth Powers to parents, Sarah Throop and Heman G. Powers, 1856-1870 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Hattie Powers Etheridge to parents, Sarah Throop and Heman G. Powers, 1872-1884 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Hattie Powers Etheridge to parents, Sarah Throop and Heman G. Powers, 1887-1892 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Hattie E. Powers to grandmother, Sarah Fales Throop, 1861 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - George Throop and Sarah Fales Throop (grandparents) to Hattie E. Powers, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Letters to Hattie Powers on the death of Sarah Fales Throop (grandmother), 1863 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Heman G. Powers (father) to Hattie E. Powers, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - William (Will) Brewer (son-in-law) to Hattie Etheridge, 1913-1918 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      William Brewer married Hattie Etheridge's daughter Emily in 1915. He served in France in World War I.
    - Elizabeth Duane to Hattie Powers Etheridge, 1913-1926 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - James H. Etheridge, telegram to Hattie Powers Etheridge, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Mary Powers Hicks to Hattie Powers Etheridge, 1913-1922 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Fanny ("Billy") Etheridge to grandparents, Heman and Sarah Powers, 1889-1890 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Emily E. Brewer to Fanny Etheridge, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Clinton Furbish to "Billy" (Fanny Etheridge), 1893-1902 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Mary Albin Throop to Fanny Etheridge, 1878 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Ruthven Pike to Fanny Etheridge Grant, 1908 March 19 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence of Emily Etheridge with grandparents, Heman and Sarah Powers, 1882-1890 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Letters to/from Heman G. and Sarah E. Throop Powers, Subseries 2
    - Emily E. Brewer, Keeseville, N.Y., to cousins Sarah and Heman, 1855-1878 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Emily E. Brewer, Keeseville, N.Y., to Heman G. and Sarah Powers, ca. 1880-1892 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      Some of the letters run to multiple numbered pages. Pages may be out of order and not linked with the correct beginning of the letter.
    - Mary Burtt, Kalamazoo, Mich., to Sarah Powers, 1852-1876 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Munro Burtt, Kalamazoo, Mich., to Heman G. Powers, 1861-1887 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Heman G. Powers to Molly Rogers Calhoun, no date (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - George and Mary Chahoon, Ausable Falls, N.Y., to Heman and Sarah Powers, 1884-1891 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      They were associated with J. & J. Rogers Iron Company.
    - W. F. Coolbaugh, Chicago, to Heman G. Powers, 1861-1876 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      W. F. Coolbaugh was president of the Union National Bank, Chicago.
    - William W. Fairwell, Chicago, to Heman G. Powers, 1883-1888 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Chas. H. Foote, Ausable Forks, N.Y., to Heman G. Powers, 1856-1860 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Mary P. Frazer to Heman G. and Sarah Powers, 1866-1872 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Clinton Furbish, Brooklyn, N.Y., to Heman G. Powers, 1877-1890 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - H. D. Graves, Ausable Forks, N.Y., to Heman G. Powers, 1856, 1886-1891 (Box 5, Folder 29)
      H. D. Graves and Kate Rogers Graves (next folder) were associated with the J. & J. Rogers Iron Co.
    - Kate Rogers Graves to Heman G. and Sarah Powers, 1854-1891 (Box 5, Folder 30)
      Kate Rogers Graves was a close relative of Heman G. Powers. In the correspondence, she was Kate Rogers until the early 1860s when she married H. D. Graves. See also Mary Rogers.
    - Henry Green to Heman G. Powers, 1856-1864 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      Green was possibly Heman G. Powers' brother-in-law. His sister Elizabeth married a Henry Green.
    - Mary Albin Throop Hallock to Sarah Throop Powers, 1856-1892 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      Mary Albin Throop was Sarah's sister. Later letters were written from Saranac Lake, N.Y.
    - W. W. Hartwell, Plattsburgh, N.Y., to Heman G. Powers, 1855-1891 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Caroline Keeler, Keeseville, N.Y., to Sarah and Heman Powers, 1864-1892 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Sarah E. Keeler, Keeseville, N.Y., to "Cousin Sarah" [Sarah Powers], 1886-1890 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Mrs. M. A. Keise [or Kuse] to Heman Powers, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - H. F. Leavitt, Middlebury Female Seminary, to Heman G. Powers, 1862-1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - John F. McGuire, Clinton, Iowa, to Heman G. Powers, 1877-1878 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Frank H. Palmer to Heman G. Powers, 1865 December 29 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Julia and W. B. Parkinson, Oshkosh, Wisconsin, to Heman G. Powers, 1879-1885 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Julia Parkinson called Heman G. Powers "Uncle Heman."
    - Ruthven W. Pike to Heman G. Powers, 1884-1890 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Emily Church Powers to parents, Sarah Throop and Heman G. Powers, 1860-1874 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Emily Church Powers was born in 1847.
    - Heman G. Powers to Sarah Powers (wife), 1872-1885 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Major Powers (father) to Heman G. Powers, 1879 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Sarah Fales Powers to parents, Heman G. and Sarah Powers, 1880-1887 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Sarah Fales Powers (1865-1924) was the youngest child of Heman G. and Sarah Throop Powers.
    - J. C. C. Reynolds, Keeseville, N.Y., to Heman G. Powers, 1871-1891 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - James Rogers, Ausable Forks, N.Y., to Heman G. Powers, 1855-1890 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Rogers was associated with the J. & J. Rogers Iron Company. The last item concerns the estate of James Rogers. See also Kate Rogers Graves.
    - Mary Rogers, Ausable Forks, N.Y., to Heman G. Powers, 1857-1868 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Heman G. Powers to Mssrs. Rogers, Martin & Co., Ausable Forks, N.Y., 1855 April 13 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - L. B. Sidway to Heman G. Powers, 1878-1879 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Roswell Skeel to Heman G. Powers, 1871, 1891, and no date (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - J. D. Smith, Vergennes, Vermont, to Heman G. Powers, 1876-1888 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - George Throop (father-in-law) to Heman G. Powers, 1854-1873 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      George Throop was the father of Sarah Throop Powers, wife of Heman G. Powers.
    - Lucia Throop to Sarah Throop Powers, 1860 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Sarah Fales Throop (mother) and George Throop (father) to Sarah Throop Powers, 1848-1863 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Harriet Powers Watson and Thomas Watson and family to Heman G. and Sarah Powers, 1859-1881 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Hester Witherspoon to Sarah Powers, 1865-1889 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - C. T. Wheeler, Chicago, to Heman G. Powers, 1889-1891 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Letters to Heman G. Powers from abroad, unidentified writers, 1866-1879 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      These were grouped together by Harriet Etheridge or other family member.
    - Miscellaneous letters to Heman G. Powers, 1872-1891 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous letters to Sarah Powers, 1886 and no date (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Documents on the funeral of Major Powers, father of Heman G. Powers, 1879 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Heman G. Powers, Bonds, agreements, and other legal papers, 1855-1868 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Supreme Court of Illinois: Henry W. Kingsbury vs. Heman G. Powers, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Printed pamphlet, "Appellee's closing Argument on Rehearing"; and Finding of the Supreme Court. Ruthven W. Pike served as attorney for Powers.
    - Heman G. Powers, Receipts from abroad, 1868 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Estate of Jeremiah B. Briggs, Heman G. Powers Administrator, 1881-1885 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Other family correspondence, Subseries 3
    - Sarah Fales Throop to grandchildren, 1862 June 30 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      Sarah Throop was the mother of Sarah Throop Powers. She was writing to grandchildren, Emmy, Hattie, and Lottie Powers.
    - Sarah Fales Throop to Mary, no date (Box 6, Folder 32)
      Probably to her daughter, Mary Albin.
    - Emily Church Powers, correspondence with Sarah Fales Throop (grandmother), 1853-1860 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Heman R. Powers, miscellaneous correspondence, 1892 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Heman R. Powers, Trip to Carthage, Missouri with J. H. Etheridge and mining agreement, 1894-1896 (Box 6, Folder 35)
      Folder contains a list of expenses for the trip in December 1894, and an agreement signed in 1896 that Fred B. Norton have exclusive mining rights for a defined parcel of land. See correspondence of James H. Etheridge and Heman R. Powers in Box 2 and Box 4.
    - Sarah Fales Powers miscellaneous correspondence (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Suzie F. Powers to parents, 1874-1884 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - "Mrs. Currier" to "Uncle Dudley", 1867-1876 (Box 6, Folder 38)
      One letter has been annotated "Mrs. Frank Palmer."
    - Clinton Furbish to "Fred", 1885 June-July (Box 6, Folder 39)
      About the delayed manufacture of an invention.
    - Letters concerning the Powers Estate, 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 40)
      Miscellaneous pages from two letters by an unidentified family member.
    - Copy of the will of Eliza Pratt, 1884 February 22 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      It is not clear how this handwritten will relates to the Throop, Powers, and Etheridge families.
    - Miscellaneous receipts, 1903 and no date (Box 6, Folder 42)
      The 1903 receipt is addressed to "Mademoiselle Etheridge" and is for jewelry from A. F. Glatour, Geneva and Cannes.
    - Recipes (Box 6, Folder 43)
      Two pages of handwritten recipes and a printed advertisement for Dr. J. B. Prescott's Canker Syrup.
    - Printed obituaries saved by the Etheridge or Powers family, 1896-1914 (Box 6, Folder 44)
      Obituaries of William H. Swan (1896), Heman R. Powers (1901), William Edward Clarke, M.D. (1898), and Roswell Park, M.D. (1914).
- J. H. Etheridge writings, Series 4
  - Articles/Reprints, 1874 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Articles/Reprints, 1880-1889 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Articles/Reprints, 1890-1894 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Articles/Reprints, 1895-1899 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - J.H. Etheridge, "A Case of Uterine Myofibroma by Enucleation and Drainage through the Cavum Uteri," W.S.O.&G., 1894 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Entire bound volume of the Proceedings of the Western Association of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 1893-1894. Etheridge's presentation is on pp. 37-41.
  - "Menstruation," typescript, no date (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript draft obituary of William Wright Jaggard (1857-1896), ca. 1896 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Presentation to a society on fever (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Ode upon the occasion of receiving -- a delicious maple caramel cake" (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - James H. Etheridge and Harriet E. Etheridge, "Our Little Fanny", 1872-1876 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    "Biographical Notes on our first little Daughter, born May 23d. 1871. By J.H. and H.E. Etheridge." Leather volume, labelled in gold leaf, "Our Little Fanny, contains entries on Fanny's early years, photographs of Dr. and Mrs. Etheridge and baby Fanny, and a lock of Fanny's hair. The Etheridges later had another daughter, Emma (or Emily).
- Organizations and societies, Series 5
  - Rush Medical College, Annual Announcements, 1884-1885, 1889-1890, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - The Corpuscle, edited by the Students of Rush Medical College, 1891-1893 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Five issues. Issues contain references to faculty members including Etheridge. See Box 1 for another issue containing an obituary of Etheridge.
  - Rush Medical College ephemera (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Contains a new year's card, clippings, and a small engraving of Rush Medical College. Three large photographs, one of Rush Medical College, and the other two of Etheridge operating are in Box 10.
  - American Medical Association Annual Meeting, Denver, ephemera, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 14)